A Guide to the James Whitcomb Riley Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #7133-r
James Whitcomb Riley Collection 1876-1913
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
7133-r
ca. 150 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit
Item Listing
- Manuscripts
  - Poem, "After Death", n.d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem beginning, "And I have come through life...", AMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, "The Arrow and the Song" filed w/ "The Empty Song", AMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, "The Assassin", n.d.; AMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, "Back From a Two-Years' Sentence", n.d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem, "The Ballad of the Coming of the Rain", n.d.; AMsS, 2 p.
  - Poem, "Being His Mother", n.d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem beginning, "Belike a hundred bards..." filed w/"To Meredith Nicholson, Jr.", AMs, 1 p.
  - Poem beginning, " 'Cause Herbert Graham's a only child...", n.d.; AMs, 2 p.
  - Story, "The Champion Checker-Player" by [ Benjamin Johnson], n.d.; AMs, 2 p.
  - Poem, "A Change", n.d.; AMsS, 2 p.
  - Story, "Child's Version of Red Riding Hood", n.d.; AMs, 6 p.
  - Poem beginning, "The cricket's call...", n.d.; AMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, "Cuored O'Skeerin", n.d.; AMs (incom.), 1 p.
  - Poem, "Down on Wriggle Creek", n.d.; AMsS, 4 p.
  - Poem, "Dream", n.d.; AMsS, 2 p.
  - Early and later versions of poem, "The Drum", 2 AMsS, 3 p. and 2 p.
  - Poem, "The Drum", n.d.; TMs, 2 p.
  - Poem, "A Dubious 'Old Kriss' ", n.d.; AMs, 3 p.
  - Poem beginning, "D was a dandyfied dog...", AMs, w/drawing, 1 p.
  - Poem, "Ef I Had My Druthers", n.d.; AMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, "The Empty Song", n.d.; AMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, "Even As a Child", n.d.; AMs (incom.), 1 p.
  - From "The Flying Islands of the Night", AMs (quotation), 1 p.
  - Poem, "The Flying Islands of the Night", AMs (incom.), 10 p.
  - Poem beginning, "For he had riz,...", n.d.; AMsS (incom.), 2 p.
  - Poem beginning, "'Fore he went to Floridy..", n.d.; AMs (incom.), 3 p.
  - Poem, "For November", 1896 Nov 2; AMsS, 2 p.
  - Poem, "Friday Afternoon" w/AMs draft of last stanza, n.d.; AMsS, 6 p.
  - Poem, "Friday Afternoon" w/auto. corr., n.d.; TMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, "Give Me the Baby To Hold", n.d.; AMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, "Glamour", n.d.; AMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, "Going To the Fair", n.d.; AMs, 1 p.
  - Poem beginning, "He hath small store...." filed w/"To Meredith Nicholson, Jr.", n.d.; AMs, 1 p.
  - Beginning, "Heart of Mankind...", 1877 Easter; AMsS (quotation), 1 p.
  - Poem, "The Hired Man Speaks", n.d.; AMs, 5 p.
  - Poem beginning, "Home' Home' O beckoning hands...", AMs on envelope
  - Poem beginning, "I dream that God..." filed w/"Judith", n.d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem, "An Idiot", n.d.; AMs, 2 p.
  - Poem, "An Idyl of the Orient", n.d.; AMs, 5 p.
  - Poem, [''Impossible Sixth Takes Me West"], n.d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem beginning, "In days to come..", AMs (incom.), 1 p.
  - Poem, "Judith", n.d.; AMsS, 2 p.
  - Poem, "Just a Fiddler", n.d.; AMsS (photostats), 4 p.
  - Early draft of poem, "Knee-Deep in June...", n.d.; AMs (incom.), 1 p.
  - Poem, "Kriss Kringle", n.d.; AMsS, 2 p.
  - Poem, "Leedle Dutch Baby", n.d.; AMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, "The Legend Glorified", AMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, "The Lesson of a Life", n.d.; AMs (incom.), 3 p.
  - Poem beginning, "Let me come in..." [trans. made by Lesley Payne], n.d.; AMs (trans.), 3 p.
  - Poem, "Marthy Ellen", n.d.; AMs, 1 p.
  - Poem beginning, "Martin and Jim...", AMs on verso of envelope
  - Poem beginning, "Mellow hazes lowly trailing...", n.d.; AMs, 3 p.
  - Poem, "My Ghoul", n.d.; AMsS, 2 p.
  - Poem, "Night", n.d.; AMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, "A Nightmare", n.d.; AMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, "Nonsense Jingles", n.d.; AMsS, 2 p.
  - Poem, "Noon", n.d.; AMs, 1 p.
  - Poem beginning, "Now, I tell you..", n.d.; AMs (incom.), 1 p.
  - Beginning, "Oh,-taken from a Cychological standpoint...", AMs, w/drawing, 1 p.
  - Last 2 leaves of poem, "Old Man" [first 3 leaves of poem in 7133-p], n.d.; AMsS (incom.), 2 p.
  - Poem, "Old Man and Jim", AMsS, 4 p.
  - Poem, "The Old Man and Jim", AMs, 4 p.
  - Poem, "Only", n.d.; AMsS, 2 p.
  - Poem, "The Opium Eater", n.d.; AMs (incom.), 2 p.
  - Poem, ["Proem"], n.d.; AMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, "Puck", n.d.; AMs (incom.), 1 p.
  - Poem, "A Quiet Lodger" with 1 discarded stanza, n.d.; AMsS, 3 p.
  - Poem, "Rest", n.d.; AMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, "A Rose in October", n.d.; AMs, 1 p.
  - From "Rubaiyat of Doc Sifers", n.d.; AMs (quotation), 1 p.
  - "Rubaiyat of Doc Sifers", n.d.; AMs (incom.), 6 p.
  - Poem, "Say Farewell and Let Me Go", AMs, 2 p.
  - Poem, "Say Something", n.d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem, "Scotty", n.d.; AMsS, 2 p.
  - Poem beginning, "Settin' round the stove..", AMs, 1 p.
  - Poem beginning, "She said so much...", [1887]; AMs on verso of envelope
  - Poem, "Some of Bub's Scattering Remarks" filed w/"'Cause Herbert Graham's a only child...", n.d.; AMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, "Song", n.d.; AMs, 1 p.
  - Poem beginning, "Sorrowfully, yet the sweeter...", n.d.; AMs (incom.), 1 p.
  - Poem, "The Stepmother", [1888]; AMs on verso of envelope
  - Poem, "Tailholt", n.d.; AMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, "T. C. Philips", n.d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem, beginning, "T was a turtle..." filed w/"D was a dandyfied dog...", AMs, w/drawing, 1 p.
  - Poem, "Thanksgiving Day at Hunchley's", n.d.; AMs, 4 p.
  - Poem, "Them Old Cheery Words', n.d.; TMs (carbon), 1 p.
  - Poem, "This Man Jones", n.d.; AMs, 4 p.
  - Poems, "To Meredith Nicholson, Jr." and "To Miss 'Sitto Nickouson' " on verso of subpoena, [1904]; 2AMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, "To - R.H.S.", 1897 May 25; AMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, "A Treat Ode", n.d.; AMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, "Uncle Sidney", n.d.; AMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, "Up and Down Old Brandywine", AMsS, 5 p.
  - Drafts of poem, "The Wandering Jew", 2 AMsS, 2 p. each
  - Poem, "What a Dead Man Said", n.d.; AMsS, 2 p.
  - Poem, "When Dickey First Dawned on Us", AMs on envelope
  - Poem beginning, "When Kate Douglas Wiggin Riggs entered on high...", n.d.; AMs on envelope
  - Poem beginning, "When she comes home again' ", n.d.; AMs, 1 p.
  - Poem, "When the Autumn Comes", n.d.; AMs, 4 p.
  - Poem, "Where Shall We Land?", AMsS, 2 p.
  - Notes re: speech by James Whitcomb Riley, n.d.; AMs on envelope
- Letters
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Editor of the Dispatch, 1877 Jul 23; Photostat of ALS, 2 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Parker, 1882 Jun 6; Photostat of ALS, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Mary Riley, 1885 Jan 9; ALS, 2 p. w/env
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Mary Riley, 1886 Jan 14; Telegram
  - [ James Whitcomb Riley] to [George] Smith, 1887 Sep 10; Photostat of ALS (incom.), w/drawing, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to George [Smith], 1891 Aug 25; Photostat of ALS, 1 p.
  - Benjamin Leggett to James Whitcomb Riley, 1892 Sep 28; ALS, 1 p. w/env
  - J. L. Thompson to James Whitcomb Riley, w/draft of ALS reply on verso of envelope, 1900 Jan 2; ALS, 1 p. w/env
  - J. L. Thompson to James Whitcomb Riley, 1900 Jan 6; ALS, 1 p. w/env
  - Catherine Beveridge to James Whitcomb Riley, [1913] Jan 3; ALS, 3 p. w/env
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Mary Riley, n.d.; ALS, 1 p. w/env
  - Catherine Beveridge to James Whitcomb Riley, n.d.; ALS, 3 p. w/env
  - James Whitcomb Riley to [ Lesley Payne], n.d.; Photostats of ALS, 2 p.
- Photographs
  - James Whitcomb Riley, seated, n.d.; 3 copies of photo
- Miscellaneous
  - For James Whitcomb Riley's speeches, 1876-1890, n.d.; 7 advertising circulars, broadsides
  - Excerpt from the Boston Evening Star, "General Burnside", [1880]; Broadside
  - Between Amos Walker and Centreville, Indiana, for a speech by James Whitcomb Riley, 1888 Aug 7; Contract
  - Chiefly addressed by James Whitcomb Riley, 1899-1891, n.d.; 9 envelopes
  - "Sing To Me, Robin'" by [ James Whitcomb Riley], n.d.; Pencil drawing
  - Lists of people and poems, 12 AMs
  - Signed, "Barrett Eastman", n.d.; Card
  - Printed calling cards with author's name, n.d.; Calling cards